<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Art of Genome Analysis</title>
    <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Art of Genome Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://katharineme.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Julia Module Organization</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/julia-module-organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/julia-module-organization/</guid>
      <description>What is a Module? A module is a self contained unit of code with a separate global scope namespace. It can only see what is inside itself. A module is defined with module NameOfModule ... end. A module can contain files and other modules.
include vs. using include and using are two ways of accessing code in Julia. using tells Julia to reference something that has already been defined, while include tells Julia to copy and define code that was not previously defined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNA-Seq Analysis</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/rna-seq-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/rna-seq-analysis/</guid>
      <description>DNA vs. RNA Photo credit to biologydictionary.net
 To review, DNA and RNA are different molecules and hold different information. DNA is more or less fixed and consistent across all your cells, with the exception of de novo mutations (in skin cells from UV light for example), whereas RNA produced by the cell is changing all the time.
From acetylation to methylation, alternative splicing, and other regulatory mechanisms, our cells use many different strategies to specialize the way they transcribe and utilize the genome, resulting in different functions (why skin cells are different from heart cells).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JuliaDB</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/juliadb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/juliadb/</guid>
      <description>Key Features  Has two main data structures: IndexedTable and NDSparse. Can work with data that is larger than the machine RAM. Allows parallel processing with the addprocs function. Works with Dagger.jl&amp;rsquo;s save and load functions to make a sort of index file adjacent to your table which allows for fast loading and access.  Table  &amp;ldquo;Table&amp;rdquo; refers to both an IndexedTable and NDSparse Tables store data in columns Tables are typed, meaning changing a table requires returning a new table JuliaDB has few mutating operations because a new table is necessary in most cases  Indexed Table  Basically a named tuple of vectors which behaves like a vector of named tuples IndexedTable can be sorted by any number of primary keys (defined using parameter pkey).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Julia</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/julia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/julia/</guid>
      <description>The words that we have available change what we will do. Why Learn Julia? What Are the Value Propositions?  Combines Python&amp;rsquo;s usability with C++ speed  Writing a prototype of code in Python, only to later implement it in C++ for speed is a waste. Now these strengths are in one language. This is accomplished using just in time compilation. The way this works is: you write dynamic Julia code, then Julia compiles it into static Julia, then everything runs super fast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tabix</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/tabix/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/tabix/</guid>
      <description>If tabix were a character, it would be the swordsman Roronoa Zoro from One Piece, slicing through your genome data to deliver you the result you want.
Tabix is part of Samtools. It indexes a tab-delimted genome position file (VCF file for example). Once indexed, it can quickly retrieve data from any part of the file without decompressing it. Thank you Heng Li 🙏 (tabix author). Here are some things you can do with tabix to a vcf.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globbing and Regex</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/globbing-and-regex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/globbing-and-regex/</guid>
      <description>This post is all about time saving tools. Globbing is for filename completion in shell and regex is for searching text.
Globbing The asterisk means &amp;ldquo;zero or more characters&amp;rdquo; in the file glob. So this command returns all files ending in .md.
ls *.md This command returns all files starting with A and ending with .md.
ls A*.md The question mark means one unknown character in the file glob. So this command will return All.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git LFS vs Others</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/git-lfs-vs-others/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/git-lfs-vs-others/</guid>
      <description>Git LFS Git Large File Storage is a CLI and server made by Github to store large files. It integrates very nicely into the git workflow, making it easy for git users to adopt. Git LFS stores your repoistory&amp;rsquo;s large files in the Git LFS server and adds a link to your repository that points there. Which files in your repository are managed by Git LFS is specified in .gitattributes and manages by git lfs track and git lfs untrack commands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strelka</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/strelka/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/strelka/</guid>
      <description>Germline and somatic variant caller made by Illumina. All methods are optimized by default for whole genome DNA-Seq. RNA-Seq is still in development and not fully supported. For best somatic indel performance, Strelka is deisgned to be run with Manta. Somatic calls require a matched normal sample to make variant calls. The matached normal sample helps Strelka identify the germline variants versus somatic variants.
Manta A structural variant and indel caller.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/docker/</guid>
      <description>Photo credit to Medium.com
Docker makes a process with unique environment requirments run anywhere.
It&amp;rsquo;s built on the Linux kernal. When the host kernal is Windows or Unix, Docker can&amp;rsquo;t interact with it directly. To run on Windows or Mac (Unix kernal), Docker creates a Linux VM and runs containers in that VM.
To run Docker on Mac specifically, the newest and best option is to get Docker Desktop for Mac.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtualization</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/virtualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/virtualization/</guid>
      <description>Virtual Machines  Virtualize the hardware Come with complete OS and kernal Interact with the hardware via a hypervisor Run on standby Start in minutes Usually GBs in size  Containers  Virtualize the OS Interact with and use the host OS and host kernal  Docker does this via Docker Daemon   Will exit without an active process Start in seconds Usually MBs in size  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence Analysis Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/sequence-analysis-benchmark/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/sequence-analysis-benchmark/</guid>
      <description>Precision FDA Truth Challenge  Genome in Bottle’s NA12878 also known as HG001. Used to develop the actual tools (overfitted to analyzing this sample). So using this sample to test for accuracy and quality is too easy. The NA24285 sample known as HG002 (the son of an Ashkenazi trio) was about to be released from GiaB (genome in a bottle) as another truth dataset. So this challenge took advantage of that HG002 to assess SA pipelines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SAM BAM CRAM</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/sam-bam-cram/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/sam-bam-cram/</guid>
      <description>SAM is the current standard format for storing aligned sequences. It was defined by the community in the early days of the 1000 genomes project.
SAM format tutorial
Samtools commands tutorial
BAM is the compressed version of SAM.
However the newest format is CRAM. A CRAM file is about 30% the size of a BAM file. CRAM is now being adopted by important bioinformatics tools like Samtools.
Size, why are SAM /BAM files so big?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Pre-Processing</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/read-preprocessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/read-preprocessing/</guid>
      <description>Pre-processing is an umbrella term that can mean filtering out / trimming low quality reads and reads contaminated with adapter sequences, and / or correcting for sequencing baises such as batch or lane effects.
Sequencing Biases  Batch effects include any errors that occur after random fragmentation of the DNA until it is input to the flow cell.  e.g., PCR amplification and reverse transcription artifacts.   Lane effects include any errors that occur from the point at which the sample is input to the flow cell until data are output from the sequencing machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FASTQ</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/fastq/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/fastq/</guid>
      <description>File Names SampleName_S1_L001_R1_001.fastq.gz
 SampleName &amp;gt; sample name provided S1 &amp;gt; sample number based on order in list of samples. S1 is first sample on the list. L001 &amp;gt; Lane number R1 &amp;gt; Read number. Paired end sequencing must have at least one R1 file and 1 R2 file. 001 &amp;gt; The last segment is always 001.  Illumina FASTQ naming convention
Format For a single-read run, one Read 1 (R1) FASTQ file is created for each sample per flow cell lane.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encoding Basics</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/encoding-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/encoding-basics/</guid>
      <description>ASCII  Character to number mapping 0-32 are non-written symbols like breaks, sounds, etc. 33 is the first written character and is the exclamation point (!) There are 128 total ASCII characters  UTF-8  UTF-8 is capable of encoding all 1,112,064 valid character code points in Unicode using one to four one-byte code units As of November 2020, UTF-8 accounts on average for 95.8% of all web pages The first 128 characters correspond 1 to 1 with ASCII characters, a big reason for its popularity  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Library Preparation</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/library-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/library-preparation/</guid>
      <description>Initial Quality Check  Check DNA purity on Nanodrop (260/280 ratio shows RNA contamination) Check DNA concentration on Qubit Fluorometer  Fragmentation Two main options for fragmenting the DNA
 Sonication  Uses a sonication machine Pros: very little base bias in cuts made Cons: Sonication machines are expensive, difficult to cut DNA fragments smaller than 300bp   Enzyme digestion  Pros: cheaper, doesnt require large sonication machine Cons: Produces minor base % bias in first 10 bases of fragments  This bias can be easily seen in FastQC results      End Repair and A Tailing In order to ligate the necessary adapters to the fragmented sequences, the ends of the fragments need to be made compatible with those adapters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinship Estimation</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/kinship-estimation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/kinship-estimation/</guid>
      <description>Two adults think they may be related based off old photos and records. How do we know for sure? That&amp;rsquo;s the topic of this post.
If it had not been for a potential family member entering our lives, I probably never would have written this. It provided the necessary motivation to learn how kinship estimation works. In this post I give an introduction to kinship from a genetic perspective. Then I describe how I did the genetic kinship analysis to discover I have another family member.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Design</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/posts/web-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/posts/web-design/</guid>
      <description>Fonts Pair a bold serif header with a nondescript sans-serif subheader for an approachabe yet sophisticated look.
Serif
 Has “serifs” at the end of the letters Its the oldest font, from 15th century Gives a trustworthy classic feeling  Sans-serif
 Simpler, cleaner, modern, no serifs  Slab serif
 Has thick slab -like serifs  Visual Hierarchy Golden Ratio 1.618 Golden ratio typography
Hick’s Law With every additional choice increases the time required to make a decision.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
