<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Beginnings on Genome Analysis Blog</title>
    <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Beginnings on Genome Analysis Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://katharineme.com/beginnings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>JuliaDB</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/juliadb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/juliadb/</guid>
      <description>In this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to explore juliaDB.jl and how it might be used to quickly retrieve results from a VCF file.
JuliaDB has two main data structures: Table and NDSparse.
Table - tables store data in columns - tables are typed, meaning changing a table requires returning a new table - julidb has few mutating operations because a new table is necessary in most  NDSparse - Behaves like a sparse array with arbitrary indices - The keys of an NDSparse array are sorted  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/sequence-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/sequence-analysis/</guid>
      <description>The human genome is 3.3 billion base pairs long.
75% of RNA-Seq sequences will be ribosomal.
Replicates
 Technical replicate: sequence same sample 2x  NGS technical replicates are usually 97% matching or better   Biological replicate: different individual sequenced under same conditions  Reference Genomes  2 major verisons  GRCh  NIH Genome Reference Consortium Latest release is GRCh38   UCSC  Latest release is hg38 Previous release was hg19 After hg19 they decided to jump release number to match GRCh      Decoy Genomes When you sequence a human genome, you dont just get human DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trace Ancestry Through DNA</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</guid>
      <description>Method 1: BioJulia&amp;rsquo;s GeneticVariation.jl https://github.com/BioJulia/GeneticVariation.jl/blob/master/docs/src/man/io/vcf-bcf.md
BioJulia is an open source project / organization that makes biology tools with Julia. They are actively maintaining many of their repositories. However GeneticVariation.jl has less commit and hasnt been updated much in the last two years. It only has 20 stars and is overall not a very active project. However, it seems to work.
But &amp;hellip;
They are query in a very manual way. THey didnt rea the vcf into a dataframe, or create an index.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trace Ancestry Through DNA</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</guid>
      <description>Ever since the human genome was sequenced in 2000, we have been trying to use it to figure out where we came from.
However, this field is at the intersection of society-wide misunderstandings about race / ethnicity, all the problems that come with a new technology (genome sequencing), and a public shortage of sequencing data for diverse human genomes. The obstacles between us and the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about our genetic heritage are currenlty great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/question/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/question/</guid>
      <description>Assuming that the reference genome is not a true human average (or even if it is) it must contain mutations that are causing a significant portion of humans problems (or at least a phenotype that makes a difference in daily life) that we aren’t paying attention to because they’re defined as “reference”, right?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
