<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Beginnings on The Art of Genome Analysis</title>
    <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Beginnings on The Art of Genome Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://katharineme.com/beginnings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Submitting an App to the App Store</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/submitting_an_app_to_the_app_store/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/submitting_an_app_to_the_app_store/</guid>
      <description>HEADS UP Before getting into the step by step process, you need to know the following about submitting an app to the app store:
 The first step is applying the the Apple Developer Program and it takes months to be approved. Apps needs to be submitted through Xcode. Here are two potentially helpful video tutorials if questions come up:  https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fXeDe9tafG8 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fXeDe9tafG8&amp;amp;t=84s    1. Enroll in Apple Developer Program  https://developer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genie.jl</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/genie.jl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/genie.jl/</guid>
      <description>Photo credit to Genie.jl
Julia is a wonderful new language which combines Python&amp;rsquo;s simplicity with C&amp;rsquo;s speed. So when I considered what language to use for the backend of a web app I&amp;rsquo;m making, naturally I wanted to use Julia. Python has well established web frameworks like flask and Django. But being such a new language I was concerned Julia wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have a fully developed web framework option like Python. I was happily mistaken.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/sequence-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/sequence-analysis/</guid>
      <description>The human genome is 3.3 billion base pairs long.
75% of RNA-Seq sequences will be ribosomal.
Replicates
 Technical replicate: sequence same sample 2x  NGS technical replicates are usually 97% matching or better   Biological replicate: different individual sequenced under same conditions  Reference Genomes  2 major verisons  GRCh  NIH Genome Reference Consortium Latest release is GRCh38   UCSC  Latest release is hg38 Previous release was hg19 After hg19 they decided to jump release number to match GRCh      Decoy Genomes When you sequence a human genome, you dont just get human DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trace Ancestry Through DNA</title>
      <link>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://katharineme.com/beginnings/trace-ancestry-through-dna/</guid>
      <description>Ever since the human genome was sequenced in 2000, we have been trying to use it to figure out where we came from.
However, this field is at the intersection of society-wide misunderstandings about race / ethnicity, all the problems that come with a new technology (genome sequencing), and a public shortage of sequencing data for diverse human genomes. The obstacles between us and the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about our genetic heritage are currenlty great.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
